"I just want to be perfect."
Black Swan is a drama, thriller, horror film directed by Darren Aronofsky.
A committed dancer struggles to maintain her sanity after winning the
lead role in a production of Tchaikovsky's "Swan Lake".
Nina Sayers / The Swan Queen, played by Natalie Portman.
Lily / The Black Swan, played by Mila Kunis.
Thomas Leroy / The Gentleman, played by Vincent Cassel.
Erica Sayers / The Queen, played by Barbara Hershey.
Beth Macintyre / The Dying Swan, played by Winona Ryder.
David Moreau / The Prince, played by Benjamin Millepied.
Black Swan is a 2010 American psychological horror thriller film directed by Darren Aronofsky from a
screenplay by Mark Heyman, John McLaughlin, and Andres Heinz, based on a story by Heinz.
The film stars Natalie Portman in the lead role, with Vincent Cassel, Mila
Kunis, Barbara Hershey, and Winona Ryder in supporting roles.
The plot revolves around a production of Tchaikovsky's Swan
Lake by the company of New York City Ballet.
The production requires a ballerina to play the innocent and fragile White Swan, for which the committed dancer Nina Sayers (Portman) is a
perfect fit, as well as the dark and sensual Black Swan, which are qualities better embodied by the new rival Lily (Kunis).
Nina is overwhelmed by a feeling of immense pressure when she finds herself competing for the
role, causing her to lose her tenuous grip on reality and descend into madness.
Aronofsky conceived the premise by connecting his viewings of a production of Swan Lake with an unrealized screenplay about
understudies and the notion of being haunted by a double, similar to the folklore surrounding doppelgängers.
Aronofsky cites Fyodor Dostoevsky's The Double as
another inspiration for the film.
Aronofsky also considered Black Swan a companion piece to his film The Wrestler (2008), with
both films revolving around demanding performances for different kinds of art.
He and Portman first discussed the project in 2000, and after a brief attachment to Universal
Pictures, Black Swan was produced in New York City in late 2009 by Fox Searchlight Pictures.
Portman and Kunis trained in ballet for several months prior to filming.
Black Swan premiered at the 67th Venice International Film Festival on September 1, 2010, and had a limited
release in the United States starting on December 3, before opening in wide release on December 17.
Upon release, the film received positive reviews from critics, with praise toward
Aronofsky's direction and the performances of Portman, Kunis, and Hershey.
It also emerged as a major commercial success at the box-office,
grossing $330.3 million worldwide on a $13 million budget.
The film received five nominations at the 83rd Academy Awards, including Best Picture and Best Director (Aronofsky), with Portman winning Best Actress; it also received four
nominations at the 68th Golden Globe Awards, including Best Motion Picture – Drama and Best Director (Aronofsky), with Portman winning Best Actress in a Motion Picture – Drama.
In 2021, Portman's performance was included in The New Yorker's list
of the best film performances of the 21st century.
The film explores themes of new york city,
dancing, dancer, nightmare, competition.
The tone is intense and dark and emotional.